A Guide to the Leonor Michaelis papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA181
Rockefeller Archive Center
Leonor Michaelis papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1900-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Michaelis, Leonor
FA181
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes
Scope and Contents
Includes an autobiographical sketch, bibliographies, corespondence, curriculum vitaes, manuscripts, obituaries, photographs, and reprints.
Biographical/Historical note
Leonor Michaelis (1875-1949) came to the RIMR as a Member in 1929 and stayed until his death in 1949. His educational background included a solid foundation in the humanities, especially Latin, Greek, and classical philology. He studied with such people as Waldeyer, Hertwig, DuBois-Reymond, and Emil Fischer. It was with Hertwig that he began investigating embryology. After medical school, Michaelis spent a year as an assistant to Paul Ehrlich. During that year he acquired an interest in the staining of tissues - an interest that never left him.
In 1921, Dr. Michaelis was made a Professor (Extra-ordinarius) at the University of Berlin, but went to Nagoya, Japan, instead because of the lack of laboratory space and equipment in Berlin. During his three years in Japan, he studied semipermeable membranes and continued this work after he went to Johns Hopkins as a visiting lecturer. In 1922, he published a book on oxidation-reduction potentials.
Arrangement note
Arrangement by subject.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 M582
Conditions Governing Access note
Access to this collection is restricted pending permission from Rockefeller University.
Enzymes; Enzymology; Electrochemistry; Biochemistry; Medical sciences; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Chemistry; Medical research; Proteins; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Autobiographic sketch, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Curriculum vitae, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Memorial minute by H. S. Gasser, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- NAS Biographical Memoir, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Obituaries and memorials, general, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Incomplete scientific manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bibliographies, incomplete (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Administrative Correspondence, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Administrative Correspondence, 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Administrative Correspondence, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Posthumous Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bibliography, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Reprints, 1900-1912 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Reprints, 1913-1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Reprints, 1925-1932 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reprints, 1929-1946 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Reprints, 1931-1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)